

San Francisco, California

☐ +1 510-388-2095 | ☑ daancamps@qmail.com | 🏕 campsd.qithub.io | ☑ campsd | 🛅 campsd | 📂 Daan Camps

Dated: January 11, 2024.

Staff member in Advanced Technologies Group at NERSC working on integrating quantum technologies with future HPC systems. Previously, computational mathematics postdoctoral researcher at Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory with a broad scientific interest and a passion for problem-solving. Almost 4 years research experience in quantum information and quantum algorithms, 8+ years experience in computational mathematics, and 2+ years experience as project engineer. Recent collaborations resulted in a robust publication record.

Work Experience

NERSC, Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory

Berkeley, USA

COMPUTER SYSTEMS ENGINEER/HPC ARCHITECTURE AND PERFORMANCE ENGINEER IN ADVANCED TECHNOLOGIES GROUP

Apr. 2022 - Current

- Working on integrating HPC with future quantum technologies,
- Benchmarking of heterogeneous quantum-classical systems,
- Developing and driving NERSC's quantum computing program and strategy,
- Research on quantum algorithms for scientific computing.

Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory

Berkeley, USA

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER IN COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS

Nov. 2019 - Apr. 2022

- Research on quantum information and quantum algorithms with a focus on circuit compilation and synthesis,
- Completed projects on Hamiltonian simulation, quantum chemistry, quantum linear algebra, and quantum image processing,
- Software engineering of nonlinear tensor factorization package,
- Developed QCLAB, QCLAB++, F3C, F3C++, QPIXL++ and FunFact,
- Team scientist.

KU Leuven Leuven, Belgium

Sep. 2015 - Jun. 2019 TEACHING ASSISTANT

- Exercise sessions for courses on numerical modeling and approximation, numerical mathematics,
- Mentor of master student projects.

IPCOS NV Leuven, Belgium

PROJECT ENGINEER IN DIGITAL OILFIELD TEAM

Aug. 2013 - Sep. 2015

- Deployment and maintenance of upstream production monitoring models based on real-time process data,
- Development and deployment of new data-driven pipeline leak detection models,
- Customer-oriented role: presenting on-site training sessions and providing end user support.

Skills, Competencies & Training.

Programming

- MATLAB, C++, Python, Fortran 90.
- OpenMP and MPI.
- git, CMake
- QCLAB and QCLAB++: quantum circuit development, analysis and simulation.
- F3C and F3C++: fast and scalable quantum circuit compilation for Hamiltonian simulation.

Open source projects

- QPIXL++: efficient and compressible representations for quantum images.
- FunFact: tensor algebra and deep learning via Einstein notations.

Research interests

Quantum algorithms, Scalable quantum benchmarking, Quantum circuit synthesis, Numerical linear algebra, Tensor decomposition techniques, Manifold optimization, Eigenvalue problems, Randomized algorithms, Scientific machine learning,

• Communications Excellence (Haas Business School, UC Berkeley, 2023)

Formal training

- Mathematics of Big Data: Sketching and (Multi-)Linear Algebra (MSRI Graduate Summer School, 2021)
- Fundamentals of Machine Learning (SOCN Graduate School, 2018)
- Low-Rank Tensor Techniques (Haussdorff School, 2016)

Personal & Communication

Languages

- Dutch: Native
- English: FluentFrench: Moderate
- TA for B.Sc. courses on numerical modeling and approximation, numerical mathematics at KU Leuven.

Teaching

- Mentor of M.Sc. thesis projects at KU Leuven.
- Mentor of summer interns at Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory.
- Mentor of postdoctoral researchers at Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory.

Publications & Preprints

- **2024** Efficient Quantum Trace Estimation with Reconfigurable Real-Time Circuits, Shen Y., Klymko K., Rabani E., Camps D., Van Beeumen R., Lindsey M. arXiv:2401.04176.
- 2024 Simulating dirty bosons on a quantum computer, Bassman Oftelie L., Van Beeumen R., Camps D., de Jong W., Dupont M., New Journal of Physics, DOI:10.1088/1367-2630/ad1a2d, arXiv:2210.08386.
- **k-Commutatitivity and Measurement Reduction for Expectation Values,** DelFavero B., Sarkar R., Camps D., Sawaya N., LaRose R. arXiv:2312.11840.
- 2023 *Quantum-centric Supercomputing for Materials Science: A Perspective on Challenges and Future Directions*, arXiv:2312.09733.
 - A Performance Model for Estimating the Cost of Scaling to Practical Quantum Advantage,
- 2023 Camps D., Klymko K., Austin B., Wright N. J., A, Proceedings of the SC '23 Workshops of The International Conference on High Performance Computing, Network, Storage, and Analysis, DOI:10.1145/3624062.3625533.
 - Efficient Quantum Counting and Quantum Content-Addressable Memory for DNA
- **2023** *similarity*, Balewski J., Camps D., Klymko K., Tritt A, 2023 IEEE International Conference on Quantum Computing and Engineering (QCE), DOI:10.1109/QCE57702.2023.00050, arXiv:2308.00699. *HamLib: A library of Hamiltonians for benchmarking quantum algorithms and hardware*,
- 2023 Sawaya N., Marti-Dafcik D., Ho Y., Tabor D., Bernal D., Magann A., Premaratne S., Dubey P., Matsuura A., de Jong W., Benjamin S., Parekh O., Tubman N., Klymko K., Camps D. arXiv:2306.13126.

 Estimating Eigenenergies from Quantum Dynamics: A Unified Noise-Resilient
- **Measurement-Driven Approach**, Shen Y., Camps D., Darbha S., Szasz A., Klymko K., Williams-Young D., Tubman N., Van Beeumen R. arXiv:2306.01858.
- Algebraic Compression of Free Fermionic Quantum Circuits: Particle Creation, Arbitrary
- **2023** *Lattices and Controlled Evolution*, Kökcü E., Camps D., Bassman Oftelie L., de Jong W., Van Beeumen R., Kemper A. arXiv:2303.09538.
- 2023 *QCLAB++: Simulating Quantum Circuits on GPUs*, Van Beeumen R., Camps D., Mehta N. arXiv:2303.00123.
 - Exploring Finite Temperature Properties of Materials with Quantum Computers, Powers C.,
- **2023** Bassman Oftelie L., Camps D., de Jong W. A., Scientific Reports, DOI: 10.1038/s41598-023-28317-5, arXiv:2205.00081.
 - Quantum-parallel vectorized data encodings and computations on trapped-ions and
- **2023** *transmon QPUs*, Balewski J., Amankwah M., Van Beeumen R., Bethel E., Perciano T., Camps D. arXiv:2301.07841.

- FABLE: Fast Approximate Quantum Circuits for Block-Encodings, Camps D., Van Beeumen R.

 2022 IEEE International Conference on Quantum Computing and Engineering (QCE), DOI:
- **Explicit Quantum Circuits for Block Encodings of Certain Sparse Matrices**, Camps D., Lin L., Van Beeumen R., Yang C., arXiv:2203.10236. Accepted in SIAM J. Matrix Anal. Appl.

Quantum pixel representations and compression for N-dimensional images, Amankwah M.

2022 G., Camps D., Bethel E.W., Van Beeumen R., Perciano T. Scientific Reports, DOI: 10.1038/s41598-022-11024-y.

10.1109/QCE53715.2022.00029, arXiv:2205.00081.

Algebraic compression of quantum circuits for Hamiltonian evolution, Kökcü E., Camps D.,

- 2022 Bassman L., Freericks J.K., de Jong W.A., Van Beeumen R., Kemper A.F., Phys. Rev. A,DOI:10.1103/PhysRevA.105.032420.
 - An algebraic quantum circuit compression algorithm for Hamiltonian simulation, Camps D.,
- **2021** Kökcü E., Bassman L., de Jong W.A., Kemper A.F., Van Beeumen R., SIAM J. Matrix Anal. Appl. 43(3), DOI:10.1137/21M1439298,arXiv:2108.03283.
- 2021 A multishift, multipole rational QZ method with aggressive early deflation, Steel T., Camps D., Meerbergen K., Vandebril R., SIAM J. Matrix Anal. Appl. 42(2), 753–774. DOI: 10.1137/19M1249631
- 2020 Approximate quantum circuit synthesis using block encodings, Camps D., Van Beeumen R., Phys. Rev. A 102, 052411. DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevA.102.052411
 - Chemistry on quantum computers with virtual quantum subspace expansion, Urbanek M.,
- **2020** Camps D., Van Beeumen R., de Jong W. A., J. Chem. Theory Comput. 16(9), 5425–5431. DOI: 10.1021/acs.jctc.0c00447
- **Quantum Fourier transform revisited, Camps D.**, Van Beeumen R., Yang C., Numer. Linear Algebra Appl. 28(1). DOI: 10.1002/nla.2331
- 2020 On pole-swapping algorithms for the eigenvalue problem, Camps D., Mach T., Vandebril R., Watkins D. S., Electron. Trans. Numer. Anal. 52, 480–508. DOI: 10.1553/etna_vol52s480
- Swapping 2x2 blocks in the Schur and generalized Schur form, Camps D., Mastronardi N., Vandebril R., Van Dooren P., J. Comput. Appl. Math. 373. 112274. DOI: 10.1016/j.cam.2019.05.022
- **A rational QZ method**, Camps D., Meerbergen K., Vandebril R., SIAM J. Matrix Anal. Appl. 40(3), 943–972. DOI: 10.1137/18M1170480
- An implicit filter for rational Krylov using core transformations, Camps D., Meerbergen K., Vandebril R., Linear Algebra and its Applications, DOI: 10.1016/j.laa.2018.09.021

 Block term decomposition for modelling epileptic seizures, Hunyadi B., Camps D., Sorber L.,
- 2014 Van Paesschen W., De Vos M., Van Huffel S., De Lathauwer L., EURASIP Journal on Advances in Signal Processing, DOI: 10.1186/1687-6180-2014-139

Education

KU Leuven (University of Leuven)

PhD in Computer Science and Applied Mathematics

Sep. 2015 - Sep. 2019

Leuven, Belgium

- Thesis: Pole swapping methods for the eigenvalue problem Rational QR algorithms.
- Generalized dense QR eigenvalue algorithms to rational QR methods.
- Implicitly restarted rational Krylov methods for large-scale, sparse eigenvalue problems.
- Focus on theory, numerical stability and efficient implementations.

KU Leuven (University of Leuven)

M.Sc.Eng. in Mathematical Engineering

Leuven, Belgium Sep. 2011 - Jun. 2013

• Thesis: 'Epileptic seizure monitoring using tensor decomposition techniques'.

KU Leuven (University of Leuven)

Leuven, Belgium

M.Sc. IN PHYSICS: ASTRONOMY AND ASTROPHYSICSThesis: 'Heschel/PACS observations of water in the carbon-rich AGB star V Hya'.

Sep. 2009 - Sep. 2011

UHasselt (University of Hasselt)

Hasselt, Belgium

B.Sc. in Physics

Sep. 2006 - Jun. 2010

Talks

Intel Labs Quantum Seminar Series Algebraic Compression of Free Fermionic Quantum Circuits	<i>Virtual</i> September 2023
10th International Congress on Industrial and Applied Mathematics FunFact: Tensor Decomposition, Your Way	Tokyo, Japan August 2023
IonQ Quantum Seminar Series Algebraic Compression of Free Fermionic Quantum Circuits	Virtual May 2023
Guest lecture at San Francisco State University Algebraic Compression of Free Fermionic Quantum Circuits	San Francisco, CA, USA April 2023
APS March Meeting Classical and Quantum Strategies to Boost Quantum Subspace Methods	Las Vegas, NV, USA Mar. 2023
IEEE International Conference on Quantum Computing and Engineering FABLE: Fast Approximate Quantum Circuits for Block-Encodings	Broomfield, CO, USA September 2022
XXI Householder Symposium on Numerical Linear Algebra An Algebraic Quantum Circuit Compression Algorithm for Hamiltonian Simulation	Selva di Fasano, Italy June 2022
CS Area 3rd Annual Postdoc Symposium FunFact: a Tensor Algebra Language with Applications in Deep Learning	Berkeley, USA Feb. 2022
SIAM Conference on Applied Linear Algebra Approximate quantum circuit synthesis using block encodings	Virtual May 2021
AIDE-QC All-Hands Meeting An Algebraic and Scalable Synthesis Algorithm for Computing Dynamic Simulation Constant-Depth Circuits	Virtual Apr. 2021
APS March Meeting Approximate quantum circuit synthesis using block encodings	Virtual Mar. 2021
SIAM Conference on Computational Science and Engineering Understanding the quantum Fourier transform through matrix decompositions	Virtual Mar. 2021
QIP Conference Approximate quantum circuit synthesis using block encodings	Virtual (Munich, Germany) Feb. 2021
CS Area 2nd Annual Postdoc Symposium Approximate quantum circuit synthesis using block encodings	Berkeley, USA Feb. 2021
Berkeley Lab Seminar Pole swapping methods for the eigenvalue problem – Rational QR algorithms	Berkeley, USA Sep. 2019
ICIAM Conference Pole swapping methods for the eigenvalue problem – Rational QR algorithms	Valencia, Spain Jul. 2019
ETNA25 Conference Approximate inverse-free rational Krylov methods and the link with FOM and GMRES	Sardinia, Italy May 2019
NASCA Conference A rational QZ method	Kalamata, Greece Jul. 2018
SIAM Conference on Applied Linear Algebra RQZ: A rational QZ method for the generalized eigenvalue problem	Hong Kong May. 2018
NUMA Internal Seminar Rational matrix algorithms for the generalized eigenvalue problem — Iterative and direct methods	Leuven, Belgium Oct. 2017
ILAS Conference Implicit restart of the rational Krylov method — Chasing algorithms for polynomial, extended and rational Krylov	lowa, USA Jul. 2017
ILAS Conference Towards a computational efficient, implicitly restarted rational Krylov method	Leuven, Belgium Jul. 2016

Academic service

Reviewer for

IEEE Transactions on Quantum Engineering, npj Quantum Information, Quantum – the open journal for quantum science, Quantum Information & Computation, Journal of Computational Physics, Applied Mathematics and Computation, SIAM Journal on Matrix Analysis and Applications, Linear and Multilinear Algebra, Electronic Transactions on Numerical Analysis, IEEE International Conference on Quantum Computing and Engineering, IOP New Journal of Physics, ACM Transactions on Quantum Computing